Guide to the Stanford University, School of Engineering, Dean's Office, Records SC0165
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, School of Engineering, Dean's Office, records
1915-1998
bulk
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University. School of Engineering. Dean's Office
SC0165
20 Linear Feet (20 boxes)
The collection consists of general office files from the School of Engineering Dean's Office. The bulk of the papers cover the years 1925-1955. Included are subject files regarding school and departmental affairs as well as interests of the individual deans; files regarding teaching appointments of non-tenured assistants, lecturers, instructors, assistant professors and visiting faculty; annual budget files (1925-1960) and annual reports to the President (1945-1964) regarding school and departmental activites, goals, faculty achievement and funding. The collection also includes some photographs and blueprints.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The records were received via administrative transfers from the School of Engineering in 1977, 1990, and 1994.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Associated Materials
Related materials in the Stanford University Archives include the Frederick E. Terman Papers, the Samuel B. Morris Papers, and the Mechanical Engineering Department Records.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Civil and mechanical engineering courses were among the first taught at Stanford University, with courses in electrical and mining engineering added in 1893. In 1925, the formerly independent engineering departments were organized into the School of Engineering with Theodore Jesse Hoover as Dean. Hoover was succeeded in 1936 by Samuel B. Morris, former director of the Pasadena municipal water system and a respected civil engineer. The School experienced its greatest development during the deanship of Frederick E. Terman, 1945-1960, formerly the executive head of the Electrical Engineering Department. Important connections were made between the school and local industry, and the School began to draw significant government contracts and grants to support graduate and faculty research. Although Terman was appointed University Provost in 1955, he remained dean until Joseph M. Pettit, Professor of Electrical Engineering, succeeded him. Pettit resigned in 1971 to become president of Georgia Institute of Technology and was succeeded by William Kays, chairman of the Mechanical Engineering department. The School now includes nine departments, with numerous laboratories and research centers.
Description of the Collection
The collection consists of general office files from the School of Engineering Dean's Office. The bulk of the papers cover the years 1925-1955. Included are subject files regarding school and departmental affairs as well as interests of the individual deans; files regarding teaching appointments of non-tenured assistants, lecturers, instructors, assistant professors and visiting faculty; annual budget files (1925-1960) and annual reports to the President (1945-1964) regarding school and departmental activites, goals, faculty achievement and funding. The collection also includes some photographs and blueprints.
Klystrons.; Photoprints.; Blueprints.; Annual reports.; Student political activity.; World War, 1939-1945; Engineering.; Tresidder, Donald Bertrand; Marx, Charles.; Kays, William M.; Hotchkiss, Willard.; Hoover, Theodore Jesse; Stanford University. Department of Electrical Engineering; Wilbur, Ray L. (Ray Lyman); Stanford University. Department of Mechanical Engineering; Stanford University. Reserve Officers Training Corps; Crothers, George E. (George Edward); Hoover, Herbert; Stanford University. Department of Mining and Metallurgy; Stanford University. Department of Civil Engineering; Stanford University. School of Engineering. Dean's Office; Stanford University. Ryan High Voltage Laboratory; Marx, Guido H. (Guido Hugo); Skilling, Hugh Hildreth; Stanford University. School of Engineering. Dean's Office; Rice, Archie.; Webster, David Locke; Terman, Frederick Emmons, 1900-1982; Pettit, Joseph M.; Willis, Bailey; Morris, Samuel Brooks.
- General Correspondence, Series 1
  - Administrative Engineering, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Memoranda, primarily between Dean Hoover and President Wilbur about proposed 2-year curricurum in civil Engineering Administration.
  - Agriculture, Department of, 1927-1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence between U.S. Department of Agriculture and Dean Hoover about employment of Stanford engineering students; requests for publications.
  - American Council on Education, 1924-1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Primarily informational material published by Councit; some correspondence from Dean's office requesting publications.
  - American Engineering Council, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    "Progress Report of Comrnittee on the Relation of Consumption, Production, and Distribution...1932." Correspondence with Dean Hoover about this report; results of surveys taken of engineering graduates.
  - American Institute of Mining and Metallurgy, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Announcement of competition for student papers on mining; correspondence with Dean Hoover about his membership status.
  - Applied Electronics Laboratory: Sit-in, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Materials related to the April 3rd Movement (anti-war group) occupation of the AEL to protest Departrment of Defense sponsored research there. Includes press releases, memoranda, eyewitness reports, flyerS and other ephemeral materials.
  - Applied Electronics Laboratory: Sit-in, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Dean Pettit's form letter sent to all engineering alumni about the demonstration; letters of response from the alumni.
  - A - general correspondence, 1925-1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A - general correspondence, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - A - general correspondence, 1941-1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Banks, Harvey, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Correspondence between Banks (former instructor in Civil Engineering at Stanford) and Dean Morris about application for registration as Civil Engineer in California.
  - Barber, Ray, 1927, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Applicant for teaching position at Stanford. Correspondence with Dean Hoover about his qualifications and professional experience.
  - Barnes, Donald, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Personal friend of Dean Morris, and applicant for teaching position at Stanford. Was offered job, but turned it down to accept post at California Institute of Technology. Correspondence on hydrology and other topics of professional interest with Dean Morris; recommendations, curuiculum vita, and other materials in support of his application at Stanford.
  - Beard, Paul, 1929-1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Associate Professor of Civil Engineering (Sanitary Sciences). Memoranda about his appointment, travel funds, promotion, and death.
  - B. S. Degree, 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    List of engineering students graduaating with B.S.
  - Building Plans: miscellaneous, 1952-1957 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Memoranda about remodelling and space allocation in various existing Engineering buildings.
  - Buildings: Electronics Research Laboratory, 1950-1958 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Correspondence and memoranda on funding and construction of the ERL.
  - Buildings: 530-540, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Memoranda and proposals about the remodelling of classroom buildings 530 and 540.
  - Buildings: Peterson Building, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Correspondence regarding the reconstruction of Building 550 as the Thomas F. Peterson Building. Includes correspondence about the dedication ceremonies; invitations to o ceremony and responses; memoranda about design of plaque; speech given by Dean Pettit at dedication.
  - Buildings: Remodeling before 1952, 1943-1951 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Correspondence and memoranda on space allocations, and plans for various engineering remodeling projects.
  - Buildings: Ryan Laboratory, 1931-1963 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Correspondence and memoranda on corporate use of Ryan facilities; electric bi1ls; conversion of lab space for other uses; disposition of high-voltage equipment.
  - Buildings: Science Quad building plans, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Memoranda related to plans for a science quad area, incorporating engineering buildings.
  - Buildings, 1952 summer (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Memoranda related to financing and planning of several engineering classroom remodeling projects.
  - 24 Buildings: Miscellaneous, 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Correspondence and memoranda on Stauffer Chemical Engineering Building, Electronics Research Laboratory, Space Sciences Buildings (Durand and Skilling), space allocation and remodeling of existing buildings, funding proposals.
  - B - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Celite Products Company, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Correspondence between Dean Hoover and H.C. Boyden of Celite Company about possible employment at Stanford. Includes curriculum vita and other materials in support of application.
  - Centrifugal Casting Research, 1928-1934 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Correspondence between U.S. War Department and Dean Hoover about research on centrifugal casting of artillary shells.
  - Civil Engineering Department: Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Civil Engineering Department: Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1931-1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Civil Engineering Department: Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Civil Engineering Department: General Correspondence, 1920-1932 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Correspondence between Dean's Office and Civil Engineering Department on various administrative matters; also copies of correspondence generated within the department of interest to Dean's Office.
  - Civil Engineering Department: General Correspondence, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Civil Engineering Department: General Correspondence, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Civilian Defence Council, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Dean Morris was chairman of the Subcommittee on Fire Prevention in this World War II defense group. Memoranda and reports on air raid fire control and safety; civilian morale and place of the university in the war efforts.
  - Commission for Relief in Belgium: Education Foundation, 1921-1929 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Correspondence about and with Belgian students attending Stanford on Belgian Relief fellowships.
  - Committee on University Radio, 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Correspondence, memoranda, and programs concerning the Stanford Radio Hour, a weekly program featuring speeches by Stanford faculty members.
  - Commonwealth Fund, 1931-1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Correspondence about and directories of Commonwealth Fund Fellows (British University students studying at American universities).
  - Crothers, Judge George E., 1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Correspondence with Crothers, Stanford administrators, and architects about the construction of the Crothers dormitories. (Housing for graduate students, particularly in engineering and law.)
  - Crothers, Judge George E., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Crothers Memorial Hall: Architectural and Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Correspondence and memoranda concerned with Crothers Memorial Hall, the second building of the Crothers dorm complex.
  - Curriculum Committee, 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Memoranda, reports, and minutes concerned with School of Engineering curriculum.
  - Curriculum Committee, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1932-1955 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1936-1942 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - C - general correspondence, 1928-1938 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - C - general correspondence, 1939-1942 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - C - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Dams - Shasta, etc., 1928-1942 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Correspondence primarily related to arrangements for engineering students to visit the works at Shasta Dam. Also correspondence about reports on arch dam construction, and conerete vs. metal dams.
  - Dean's Meetings, 1944-1948 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Memoranda and minutes of meetings of Deans from all the Stanford schools.
  - Durand. William F., 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Professor Emeritus of Mechanical Engineering.
  - Durand dinner, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 1718)
    Memoranda regarding arrangements for testimonial dinner honoring W.F. Durand; invitations to dinner, responses.
  - D - general correspondence, 1928-1942 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - D - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Earthquake Engineering Research Institute, 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Correspondence largely of Lydik S. Jacobsen, John A. Blume, and Franklin P. Ulrich.
  - Electrical Engineering, 1925-1930 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Memoranda between the Dean's Office and Electrical Engineering Department on various administrative matters; also copies of correspondence generated within Electrical Engineering Dept. of interest to Dean's Office.
  - Electrical Engineering, 1927-1932 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Electrical Engineering, 1933-1937 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Electrical Engineering, 1938-1943 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Electrical Engineering, 1952-1957 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Electrical Engineering, Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1948-1957 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Electrical Engineering, Ryan High Voltage Lab, 1927-1942 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Correspondence and memoranda concerning use of the lab for outside testing; budgeting; general administrative concerns.
  - Engineering Advisory Council, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Committee composed of engineering faculty members to make recommendations on engineering aspects of campus architecture, grounds and utilities. Minutes, memoranda, and reports of the Council.
  - Engineering College Research Association, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    The purpose of this association was "to coordinate the services of the experiment stations and research laboratories of the colleges of the U.S. to enhance their value to the war effort."
  - Engineering College Research Association, Minutes, 1942-1945 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Engineering Foundation, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Proposals to foundation for funding of high voltage research at Stanford; reports of ongoing research made possible by foundation.
  - Engineering Fund, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Drafts of letters sent out by Stanford Engineering Fund to Stanford engineering alumni soliciting funds; comments and criticisms of letters by members of the Fund Committee.
  - Engineering Fund: Survey of Engineering Alumni, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Alumni responses to questionnaire on the quality of Stanford engineering education.
  - Engineering Loan Fund, 1936-1938, 1945-1948 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Memoranda about loans available to civil engineering students through the School of Engineering.
  - Engineering School: Executive Committee Minutes, 1925-1929 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Engineering School: Executive Committee Minutes, 1946 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Engineering School: Executive Committee Minutes, 1947 Jan-Jun (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Engineering School: Executive Committee Minutes, 1947 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Engineering School: Executive Committee Minutes, 1948 Jan-Jun (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Engineers' Council for Professional Development, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    This organization was concerned with the academic accreditation of engineering schools, faculty and curriculum nationwide. Folder contains correspondence between Dean's Office and Council on these topics; also Stanford internal memos about the organization and its goals.
  - Engineers' Council for Professional Development, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Engineers' Council for Professional Development, 1938-1941 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Engineers' Council for Professional Development, 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - E.C.P.D.: Checklist of Engineering Majors, 1938-1941 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Lists of engineering students prepared by office for E.C.P.D. statistics.
  - E.C.P.D.: Inspection of Oregon State College, Corvalis, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Dean Morris was on the Civil Engineering section of the E.C.P.D.'s visiting committee that was to determine this college's accreditation. Correspondence related to arrangements to visit; curriculum and faculty matters.
  - Executive Committee of the Academic Council: Minutes, 1948-1953 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Dean Terman was a mernber of this University-wide committee of deans and department chairmen.
  - E - General Correspondence, 1930-1942 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - E - General Correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Faculty Meetings (Engineering), Minutes, 1925-1932 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Fahrenwald, A. W., 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Candidate for teaching position in Metallurgy - was offered post, but declined for family reasons. correspondence between Dean Hoover and Fahrenwald about his appointment, delays in accepting, resignation of appointment.
  - Fiftieth Anniversary Celebration, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Dean Morris was member of Subcommittee on Institutes and Seminars to be held in conjunction with Stanford's fiftieth anniversary festivities to be held in 1941. Folder contains menoranda and informational material about arrangements for speakers, conferences, etc.
  - Fiftieth Anniversary Celebration, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Financial Awards Committee, 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Memoranda connected with university-wide cormmittee, of which Dean Terman was a member, that allocated financial awards for graduate students.
  - Foreign Students Committee, 1955-1959 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Folder contains quarterly lists of foreign students at Stanford; informational brochures for prospective foreign applicants; miscellaneous memoranda about foreign students.
  - Four-Quarter Engineering Committee, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    In 1941, Stanford began a large scale summer session effort in order to accelerate graduation for interested students. Program was created in response to World War II technical manpower needs. Folder contains materials related to planning, budget and curriculum for summer sessions.
  - Four-Two Program: Student Inquiries, 1956-1960 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Letters from prospective studenis inquiring into the four-two program, and copies of replies from engineering faculty involved. This program was designed to enable graduates from four-year liberal arts colleges that did not have engineering curricula to obtain an MS in engineering from Stanford in two years.
  - Foivler, F. H., 1938-1943 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Stanford engineering alumni, professional civil engineer, and personal friend of Dean Morris. Nominated by Morris for presidency of American Society of Civil Engineers. Folder contains conrespondence between Morris and Fowler on various personal and professional topics; also correspondence with other civil engineers in regard to ASCE presidency.
  - Freeman, John R., 1929-1934 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Consulting civil engineer. Correspondence with Dean Hoover about necessity of earthquake research at Stanford, and suggestions about research procedures.
  - Frequency Modulation Station, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Memoranda, proposals and budgets for proposed 1 Kilowatt FM radio station at Stanford.
  - Fulbright Program, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Inquiries and information about Fulbright scholarships at Stanford.
  - F - general correspondence, l935-1942 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - F - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - General Electric Educational Fund, 1947-1954 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Information on research fellowships sponsored by General Electric; applications and letters of recommendation for applicants.
  - General Secretary's Office, 1951-1958 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Memoranda between Dean's Office and GSO about fund-raising strategies; drafts of proposals for major foundation grants; miscellaneous informational material.
  - Gift Acknowledgement Letters, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Letters written by Dean Terman to donors to the School of Engineering.
  - Gift Acknowledgenent Letters, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Gift Acknowledgement Letters: A-L, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Gift Acknowledgement Letters: M-Z, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Gilfillan Brothers, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Correspondence and memoranda about the construction and budgeting of Gilfillan Wing addition to the Electronics Research Laboratory.
  - Glass, Edward, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Professional architectural and valuation engineer. Correspondence with President's and Dean's 0ffice attempting to interest Stanford in offering a course (to be taught by Glass) on engineering and architectural cost appraisals for engineers.
  - Grant, Eugene, 1928-1943 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Professor of Civil Engineering at Stanford. Application and letters of recomendation for his initial appointment at Stanford; memoranda about promotions, publications, and miscellaneous professional topics.
  - Guggenheim Laboratory, 1926-1938 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Memoranda on staffing, funding, research and administrative structure of Guggenheim Aeronautics Laboratory.
  - Guggenheim Laboratory, 1939-1942 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Guggenheim Laboratory, 1945-1954 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Guggenheim Laboratory: Postwar Training and Research, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Memoranda between Dean Morris, W. F. Durand, and President Tresidder on the post-war needs and progress in aeronautics; correspondence between executives of aeronautics industries and Dean's office on their suggestions for research direction.
  - G - general correspondence, 1920-1931 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - G - general correspondence, 1932-1937 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - G - general correspondence, 1938-1942 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - G - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Haertline, Albert, 1928, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Professor of Civil Engineering at Harvard. Applied for, and was offered teaching post at Stanford, which he had to decline because of other committments. Folder contains correspondence related to his application, and the circumstances for declining job.
  - Hedberg, John, 1931-1942 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Associate Professor of Civil Engineering at Stanford. Applications and recommendations for original appointment; memoranda on promotions, salary, departmental business; obituary by J.C.L. Fish.
  - Henline, Henry, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering. Memoranda about Henline's appointment as Stanford's delegate at annual meeting of Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education; text of his paper,"Engineering Education: Its History and Prospects" presented at AIEE meeting; prospectus for The Stanford Engineer (periodical); his letters of resignation.
  - Honors Cooperative Prograrm, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 1213)
    The Honors Cooperative Program was designed to allow professional engineers employed by local companies to pursue advanced engineering degrees part-time, at the expense of their companies. Folders include correspondence with, and lists of students employed by, the following companies: Ames, Ampex, Argonaut Underwriters, Dalmo Victor, Detroit Controls, Dynac, General Electric, Hewlett-Packard, Hiller Helicopters, IBM, Lenkurt, Link Aviation, Lockheed, Shockley Labs, Sperry Gyroscope, SRI, Sylvania, Varian, Westinghouse/
  - Honors Cooperative Program, 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Miscellaneous small companies; general regulations for participants.